[Music]
welcome back to five minutes is dr. Andy
golfing here
today's topic fitness and training
technologies the good in the bad how
they can be helpful but how they can
actually cause problems too so conflict
of interest I have a book out you can
check out more in that if you'd like but
here's the quick version number one this
is not an anti Tech Talk it's an anti
failing talk so whether you look at the
research or you talk to any of your
friends we have evidence on both sides
that suggest any of these fitness
training technologies so thank heart
rate monitors glucose monitor an app
that can tell you how much you sleep I
can measure your food for you any of
these things have they all have pros and
cons and so what I want you to
understand today is what are the pros so
you can take advantage of and then one
of the cons some that you can avoid them
so let's jump into this and do this very
quickly well all don't have some harm
has some of them have some help so the
general benefits they can answer very
specific hypotheses so they can track
things that you're very specifically
interested in large data sets so
oftentimes day to day variations and say
your sleep they're influenced too much
by something like maybe what you watched
on TV last night right before bed but
over time those small day-to-day
variations will shake themselves out and
you can start to see large trends so
technology can be very helpful for that
your your mind has a hard time kind of
wrapping itself around the long term
picture like that and the technology can
be great so long-term tracking and large
data sets if you're working with
multiple people or you're trying to
collect a ton of information on yourself
that's gonna be help to manage that with
your own brain it's also objective right
doesn't matter what you think or what
you care the heart rate monitor will
tell you what your heart is that and
doesn't matter if you want to lie and
cheat you through your training partner
or your coach it's gonna tell you if you
get your steps in today or if you did
it's quick accurate communication so you
can work directly with the coach you can
give you live feedback or you can video
your workouts to send it's your
instructor your coach and that can be
very very helpful but more important I
think these four at the bottom of the
best number one it allows
individualization so imagine that you're
in a scenario where you want to just
train for peak power today well I don't
certainly need to give you instructions
about how much to lift or how many reps
do or how much rests to take in between
your sets all I'm gonna give you is a
technology that measures the barbell or
the dumbbell or whatever you're moving
and measures power and you're gonna do
whatever it takes to get the highest
number and you'll figure that out so
that can help you individualize programs
across a lot of people or prescriptions
another example would be if you're
trying to say targets the glutes
for some reason well the same exercise
won't necessarily always target the
glutes see one of my other videos if you
want explanation of that but because we
have different limb lengths and
activation patterns and exercise
histories and Kenneth can you see
logical awareness that is not a word but
you get it body awareness technology
will allow me to say hey look realize
that this hip hinge activity you've got
program for me coach I'm like I don't
see my glutes being activated on my app
here so I need to do a different
exercise so that could be helpful for
that cause accountability we know that
right if everyone sees are you reporting
or you at least you yourself have to
physically see your numbers your
accountability as can go up now they can
actually make things worse too but it
can be beneficial awareness imagine a
food app people have no idea how many
calories are actually eating they don't
really don't know what 3 ounces looks
like or what 60 grams of carbohydrates
is so being simply aware and calibrated
the same kind of idea there and what it
actually means to get eight hours of
sleep yeah I feel pretty good what's
good pretty good mean right are you
really calibrated so with that the bad
using to midst of this Fitness
technology can blunt your own possible
feedback and so you start outsourcing
your own intelligence and what it feels
like to do something to what the
technology told you and that's a real
problem
the other issue another issue with a lot
of these training technologies they
often tell you have a problem so you're
not sleeping enough for your heart
really to be soft but they don't tell
you what to do to fix it some of them do
that but what I can tell you from behind
the scenes they're not getting that
fixed or that solution from qualified
individual all the time so it's
generally not a good idea to follow that
prescription the accuracy oh boy even
something that's basic like a heart rate
monitor or a technology that has a
hundred million dollars into it may not
be actually a
and we have a lot of science and data to
show that those things lack in accuracy
data overload right what ends up
happening of any of you that have tried
to collect big databases on yourself is
you end up not doing anything with it
and now you've wasted money and you've
wasted time the big thing though is is
technology doesn't understand context
and situational awareness so example
here's what I talk about commonly of
adaptation versus optimization so
sometimes you're trying to induce
adaptation so imagine you're using
something like a heart rate variability
which generally tells you if you're you
know fatigued or nah fatigued well if
you're a training phase where we're
trying to give accumulation of fatigue
to induce that outpatient I don't care
if you're HRV tells you're in the tanks
you know what need to take a day off
that's the point but if you're trying to
peak for competition then that same
exact score needs to be met with a
different response and it doesn't
understand other things of context like
what the goal is what are you trying to
do right so if you have a technology
that shows you how fast you're moving
the barbell more isn't always better
maybe you're trying to focus on
technique today you don't care about
speed but the app won't know that thing
so you still have to use your own
intelligence to think about what the
goal the purpose of the point of this
thing is and not just listen to whatever
the technology tells you to do alright
also those what we call ships a focus
from a dime to over a dollar so you
could use the technology to track give
yourself constant testosterone
measurement to figure out why you feel
so tired all the time or you could go
back and go oh yeah I haven't been
sleeping right so you tend to get
fixated on what the tech is instead of
looking for those big solutions
hydration food quality food sleep
happiness stress etc it can be an arms
race every single year you got to buy a
new one right because either they stop
giving updates to this one or you
realize there's another gizmo or gadget
coming and you end up spending millions
I not amazed but you spend hundreds and
hundreds and hundreds of dollars every
year on another technology and you end
up really making very few positive
changes and because of all that it
actually does what we call foster
dependence so you lose self-reliance and
gain dependence on the technology what
we should be using as a technology then
to
to wrap up to assess what we want if we
can't see things to inform us in to
calibrate us but don't treat it as an
infallible deity and has probably you
still have to think your brain is still
a way better general intelligence
monitor for your fitness and health than
any app that I've seen so far because
the goal of mastery should be to take
self identification combine that with
self correction so if you can use
technology to help you identify what's
going on but then you can get to a place
where you can identify the problem I
don't need the monitor anymore because I
realize now what it feels like when I'm
fatigued and then I also don't need the
technology to tell me what to do to
correct right so being able to help use
technology to help you get to self
identification and self correction
generally should be our goal we want to
enhance self reliance not dependence
Thanks let me know if you want more and
check out all the rest of my videos if
you enjoy this I would really appreciate
a small contribution on my patreon
account that is w patreon.com forward
slash an account
[Music]